Today's דף *daf* is פ"ח *Peh-Chet* 88 and it's like the probably
major דף *daf* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that deals with אגדתא
*Aggadata* on הר סיני Har Sinai *Har Sinai* so as we were
discussing just a minute ago often learned on שבועות Shavuot *Shavuot*. I
have a couple of interesting sources I'll be bringing in as we
get to relevant גמרות *Gemarot*. I wanted to start though by saying
you know yesterday we had the whole discussion about which we're wrapping
up today you know let's wrap it up today and then I'll
bring in this source. So starting at the top of פ"ח עמוד
א' *Peh-Chet Amud Aleph* תא שמע *Ta Shma* first line and the
debate here is between רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi *Rabbi Yosi* and the
רבנן Rabanan *Rabbanan*. Everybody agrees תורה Torah *Torah* was given on שבת
Shabbat *Shabbos*, everybody agrees that they came to הר סיני Har Sinai.
*Har Sinai* on the first of סיון Sivan *Sivan* and the question
is whether they came on a Monday or a Sunday, whether the
תורה Torah *Torah* was given on the sixth or the seventh of
סיון Sivan, *Sivan* and also it relates to that question about whether
there was two or three days of separation. Okay and we pointed
out that according to the text two things we pointed out yesterday.
One is according to the תורה Torah *Torah* sounds very clearly two
days of separation היום ומחר *Hayom Umachar* and according to רבי יוסי
Rebbe Yosi *Rabbi Yosi* that says three days he introduces this radical
concept that משה Moshe *Moshe* added a third day so in the
way God wanted to give it on Friday but because of משה
Moshe *Moshe* God chose to give it on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* decision
to add a third day. And number two something we pointed out
and mentioned it was the תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* also a passage from
the מהר"ל Maharal *Maharal* that according to both opinions the תורה Torah
*Torah* was given on the not only was the debate of the
sixth or seventh of סיון *Sivan* according to both opinions the תורה
Torah *Torah* was given on the fifty-first day of the עומר Omer
*Omer* because they both say they left מצרים Mitzrayim *Mitzrayim* on a
Thursday which meant the first day of the עומר Omer *Omer* had
they been counting the עומר Omer. *Omer* would have been a Friday
and therefore שבועות Shavuot *Shavuos* should have been a Friday but no
it was given on the fifty-first on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*. So we
wrap this up starting now at the top of the דף *daf*
תא שמע *Ta Shma* דתניא *detanya* we taught בסדר עולם *beSeder Olam*
in סדר עולם Seder Olam *Seder Olam* which is a תנאי *Tannaic*
work that basically gives the chronology of the events in the תורה
Torah *Torah* ניסן Nissan שבו יצאו ישראל ממצרים *Nisan shebo yatzu Yisrael
miMitzrayim* the ניסן *Nisan* is when בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael *Bnei Yisrael*
left מצרים *Mitzrayim* בארבעה עשר שחטו פסחיהם בחמישה עשר יצאו *be'arba'ah asar
shachatu pischayhem bechamishah asar yatzu* they שחטו *shecheted* their פסח Pesach *Pesach*
on the fourteenth they left on the fifteenth and then until now
we've been saying that that day was a Thursday which was consistent
with רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi *Rabbi Yosi* also from that תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* said that's how we get the idea of שבת Shabbat הגדול
*Shabbos HaGadol* because they took their פסח *Pesach* on the previous שבת
Shabbos. *Shabbos*. Anyway before we were saying it's a Thursday this ברייתא
braita *Braita* says ואותו היום ערב שבת erev Shabbat היה *ve'oto hayom
erev Shabbos hayah* that day was a Friday ומראש ירחא דניסן *umireish
yarcha deNisan* so if the fifteenth of ניסן *Nisan* was a Friday
then the first of ניסן *Nisan* was a Friday and if the
first of ניסן *Nisan* was a Friday
ריש ירחא דאייר חד בשבתא *reish yarcha deIyar chad beshabba* so ראש
חודש אייר *Rosh Chodesh Iyar* is always two days after or if
ניסן *Nisan* is a מלא *malei* which it always is two days
after ראש חודש ניסן *Rosh Chodesh Nisan* so therefore ראש חודש אייר
*Rosh Chodesh Iyar* was Sunday and סיון *Sivan* and אייר *Iyar* which
is a חסר *chaser* the ראש חודש סיון *Rosh Chodesh Sivan* is
one day after that so סיון בתרי בשבתא *Sivan bitrei beshabba* so
ראש חודש סיון *Rosh Chodesh Sivan* would be on a Monday which
is consistent with the רבנן Rabanan, *Rabbanan* which is that ראש חודש
*Rosh Chodesh* was a Monday so the תורה Torah *Torah* was given
on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* which would make it the sixth of סיון
*Sivan* which means it was only two days of separation. So קשיא
לרבי יוסי *kashya leRabbi Yosi* that's a challenge to רבי יוסי Rebbe
Yosi *Rabbi Yosi*. So like we've been saying all of yesterday what's
the big deal? It's a תנא *Tanna* it's you know a ברייתא
beraita *Braita* and this is the debate of תנאים Tannaim, *Tannaim*. So
אמר לך רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi *amar lach Rabbi Yosi* רבי יוסי
Rebbe Yosi *Rabbi Yosi* will say to you הא מני רבנן Rabanan,
היא *ha meni Rabbanan hi* fine that's the position of the רבנן
Rabanan *Rabbanan* that ראש חודש ניסן *Rosh Chodesh Nisan* was a Monday
but we I say that it was a Sunday. תא שמע *Ta
Shma* come and hear רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, אומר *Rabbi Yosi omer*
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yosi* says here it is רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi* himself בשני עלה משה Moshe וירד *besheni alah
Moshe veyarad* so משה Moshe *Moshe* went up and down on Monday
that was the first going up after they arrived on Sunday the
first of סיון *Sivan* they settled in then he went up on
the second on Monday the second day and God said to him
אתם תהיו לי ממלכת כהנים *atem tihyu li mamlechet kohanim* and he
came down. בשלישי עלה *beshlishi alah* he went up on the Tuesday
on the third וירד *veyarad* and he came down and that's when
according to חז"ל Chazal, *Chazal* the תורה Torah *Torah* isn't exactly clear
what he had to report to בני ישראל Bnei Yisroel *Bnei Yisrael*
there but according to the earlier גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that was also
when God gave him the מצווה *mitzvah* of הגבלה *hagbalah* of giving
a boundary around the mountain. And בארבעה *be'arba* and on the fourth
וירד *veyarad* then he came down ושוב לא עלה *veshuv lo alah*
he didn't go back up. So before we get to analyze it
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* interjects as it were one minute ומאחר שלא
עלה היכן ירד *umei'achar shelo alah heichan yarad* what do you mean
on the fourth he went down you didn't say yet that he
went up so how did he go down without going up? Okay
fine אלא ברביעי עלה וירד *ela berevi'i alah veyarad* alright fix it
he went up and came down on the fourth day and that
was where God told him the מצווה *mitzvah* of separating husbands and
wives okay and that was or more literally the word the men
from their wives and that's when there was three days of according
to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi Yosi* of separation and the תורה
Torah *Torah* given on שבת *Shabbat*. בחמישי בנה מזבח mizbeach *bechamishi banah
mizbeiach* on the following day Thursday he built the מזבח mizbeach *mizbeiach*.
Now you might not remember in the narrative in יתרו Yitro *Yitro*
there being a מזבח *mizbeiach* because it's at the end of משפטים
mishpatim *Mishpatim*. At the end of משפטים Mishpatim *Mishpatim* it says that
ואלה המשפטים *ve'eleh hamishpatim* gives all these משפטים Mishpatim *mishpatim* and then
it says and משה Moshe *Moshe*... At the end of משפטים Mishpatim
it says that אלה המשפטים eileh hamishpatim gives all these משפטים Mishpatim
and then it says and משה Moshe, built this altar and he's
sprinkled the blood and he said this is the דם הברית dam
habrit and that's by the way where they say what נעשה ונשמע
naaseh v'nishma it does not appear in the תורה's Torah narrative before
מתן תורה Matan Torah it appears at the end of משפטים but
according to many approaches in the גמרא Gemara that whole event of
the מזבח and the blood and this is the דם הברית dam
habris and the נעשה ונשמע naaseh v'nishma was before מתן תורה Matan
Torah okay and that's what this גמרא's Gemara assuming as well so
on the fifth on Thursday he did the whole thing with the
מזבח and the whole
נעשה ונשמע naaseh v'nishma והקריב עליו קרבן vehikriv alav korban and he
brought the
קרבן korban בשישי לא היה לו פנאי beshishi lo haya lo pnai
but on Friday he had no time to do go up you
know to the mountain or do anything else so what's what
מאי לאו mai lav so anyway now this is רבי יוסי himself
and this is a challenge to רבא Rava because רבא Rava was
the one that was saying that for רבי יוסי there were these
three days of separation Thursday Friday and שבת and here we have
רבי יוסי saying Friday he had no time why didn't he have
time to do anything Friday מאי לאו משום תורה mai lav mishum
Torah it must mean that Friday was the day the תורה Torah
was given now that would have been a funny way to say
the תורה Torah was given that he didn't have time so the
גמרא Gemara rejects that the גמרא Gemara says
לא משום טרחא דשבתא lo mishum tarchah d'shabta no it meant he
was busy getting ready for שבת so now they did have שבת
already you know but because that was already from המן hamann yesterday
we said from מרה Marah but that he was so busy although
that was already starting yeah what'd he have to do so I
don't know right you know הרב סולובייצ'יק Harav Soloveitchik once famously said
it's such a beautiful point that he makes I forget where he
said it he says you know he says ברוך השם Baruch Hashem
here in America you know there are you know many many שומרי
שבת shomrei Shabbat Jews he says but what he misses is שומרי
ערב שבת shomrei erev Shabbat Jews so the idea of really devoting
time on ערב שבת and investing getting ready for שבת so that
anyway that's what it means all right fine so that does it
so that's still consistent with רבי יוסי and the תורה Torah would
have been given on the next day all right one minute let's
just get to finish this point
דרש ההוא גלילאה darash hahu galila'ah a certain Galilean gave a דרשה
drasha עליה דרב חסדא aleh d'Rav Chisda standing above רב חסדא Rav
Chisda meaning רב חסדא Rav Chisda was the one that was really
sort of you know giving the שיעור shiur but you know he
was the one that everybody's coming to hear but this Galilean came
up to sort of be his דרשן darshan and to give a
דרשה drasha in his presence so and here's what he said
בריך רחמנא brich Rachmana you know because also there was often very
like this sort of stylistic way of doing of giving sermons you
see it sometimes in the שאילתות Sheiltos or a little in the
מדרש רבה Midrash Rabbah you know you would certain start with maybe
in the מדרש רבה Midrash Rabbah the way מדרש רבה Midrash Rabbah
often opens is it quotes a
פסוק pasuk seemingly unrelated it doesn't start with the first פסוק pasuk
of the פרשה parsha and then it sort of circles back to
discussing around the פרשה parsha the way the שאילתות Sheiltos begins is
it starts with sort of raising a הלכה halacha question then it
you know sort of turns into some דרשה drasha and then it
goes back to the הלכה halacha question there were certain styles of
giving sermons so presumably here they were sort of opening some type
of a sermon with discussing מתן תורה Matan Torah and here's how
he opened and it was like also like a little riddle or
something so he says בריך רחמנא דיהב אוריין תליתאי brich Rachmana d'yahiv
oryan tlitai blessed is God that has given the tripartite תורה Torah,
meaning תורה נביאים וכתובים Torah Neviim u'Ketuvim לעם תליתאי l'am tlitai to
the tripartite nation this is כהנים לויים ישראלים Kohanim Leviim Yisraelim this
is how רש"י Rashi explained it על ידי תליתאי al yedei tlitai
through a third because משה Moshe was the third he was you
know he was אהרן מרים ומשה Aharon Miriam u'Moshe ביום תליתאי b'yom
tlitai on the third day and what does it mean Thursday it
doesn't mean Tuesday because that wasn't even a possibility but the third
day of separation בירחא תליתאי b'yarcha tlitai on the third month on
סיון so כמאן keman who is that like כרבנן k'rabbanan like the
rabbis that say that the תורה Torah was given on the third
day of separation not there was three days and then it was
given on the fourth and with this we end the discussion of
the day the תורה Torah, was given two days or three days
of separation we're going to turn into
general אגדות aggadot relating to הר סיני Har Sinai yeah Charlie and
the ברייתא Braitah from the סדר עולם Seder Olam that the גמרא
Gemara says from the rabbis but the סדר עולם Seder Olam...
is written by רבי יוסי oh really is that so I forgotten
that the גמרא Gemara says סתם סדר עולם רבי יוסי
stam Seder
Olam
Rebbe Yosi yeah all right it's
a good question
that's a good question I don't know have to get back to
you on that one
yeah alright that's a good question
yeah
so according to that certainly according to רבי יוסי it was really
given on the seventh of the month so why have we so
many for generations
well that's not a problem because we don't you know if it's
we more focus on the day of what do you call it
on the day of שבועות is the day of of the עומר
Omer. but it is a problem so thank you that's a perfect
segue it is a problem because why do we celebrate you know
שבועות on which is supposedly זמן מתן תורתנו zman matan torateinu on
the 50th you know if the תורה Torah was given on the
51st
that's what I said yesterday so anyway I wanted to read you
a little passage from the מהר"ל מפראג Maharal m'Prague in his ספר
תפארת ישראל sefer Tiferet Yisrael so he says two things both sort
of echoing things we said yesterday
if they left מצרים on Thursday so then the first day of
the עומר Omer. would have been a Friday because yesterday it said
they left on a Thursday so Friday is 1, 8, 15, 22,
29, 36, 43, 50. Friday is also 50, but it said that
they got the תורה Torah on שבת. Okay, so
this results in the סדר עולם... Seder Olam yeah, this is going
to the סדר עולם זוטא Seder Olam Zuta because they left on
a Friday and it would have been the 51st day. So according
to the סדר עולם Seder Olam it works. According to everything we
said now, it's the 51st day of the עומר. So anyway, so
here's what the מהר"ל Maharal says. First, he says about this idea
of יום אחד הוסיף משה מדעתו. Yom echad hosif Moshe mi-da'ato. I
made some reference to the idea that this sort of, you know,
it sort of eludes to or could be seen as relating to
the whole idea of תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh and חז"ל,
Chazal you know, using their intellect to understand and apply the תורה
Torah and then the sense of God as מסכים על ידו. maskim
al yado. So I just wanted to read you first of all
one line he says here. He says relating to that, he says
like this. He says: ודאי כל מה שהוציאו חכמים מן הכתוב על
ידי דרשה שלהם נקרא כל דברי חכמים ודעתם אף שהוא נרמז בתורה
והוא מן התורה מכל מקום הם הוציאו הפירוש מחכמתם ודעתם ודבר זה
יתבאר בעזרת השם יתברך. Vadai kol ma she-hotziu chachamim min ha-katuv al
yedei drasha she-lahem nikra kol divrei chachamim ve-da'atam af she-hu nirmaz ba-Torah
ve-hu min ha-Torah mi-kol makom hem hotziu ha-perush mi-chochmatam ve-da'atam ve-davar zeh
yitba'er be-ezrat Hashem yitbarach. So emphasizing
what we sometimes tend to downplay, you know, the human component of
תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-ba'al peh. That even though they're learning it
from the פסוקים psukim and it has a דאורייתא, de-Oraita, it's binding
דאורייתא, de-Oraita, ultimately they're using their intellect, their creativity, their knowledge to
say that that is what the תורה Torah means. And he connects
this obviously to this יום אחד הוסיף מדעתו. Yom echad hosif mi-da'ato.
More relevant for us is day 51, which I wanted to read
to you. He says like this: ואנו אומרים בעצרת זמן מתן תורתנו
ולבדי דרבנן הוי שפיר משום
דלהוי יום ו בסיון. Ve-anu omrim be-Atzeret zman matan Toratenu u-levadai de-Rabanan
havei shapir mishum de-lehu avei yom vav be-Sivan.
So at least according to the רבנן Rabanan and not רבי יוסי,
it's the sixth of סיון, even though it doesn't work out in
terms of the day of the עומר. אבל לרבי יוסי דבז בסיון
ניתנו עשרת הדברות לא היה זמן מתן תורה. Aval le-Rabbi Yossi de-be-zayin
be-Sivan nitnu aseret ha-dibrot lo haya zman matan Torah. And then he
says also that the fact that it's 51st, he says... he says
like this: וזה מפני... Ve-zeh mipnei... and he goes on to point
out here he says like this: אבל המקבל אומר זמן מתן תורה
ביום נ רק שלא הגיעה תורה אל המקבל רק ביום נא ומכל
מקום זמן מתן תורה הוא ביום חמישים. Aval ha-mikabel omer zman matan
Torah be-yom nun rak she-lo higia Torah el ha-mikabel rak be-yom nun
aleph u-mi-kol makom zman matan Torah hu be-yom chamishim.
So what he says is that... ובזה תבין דברי רבי יוסי שאמר
יום חמישים ויום שישי שאין משמעו רק שישי בסיון בחינת מצד הנותן.
U-ve-zeh tavin divrei Rabbi Yossi she-amar yom chamishim ve-yom shishi she-ein mashmao
rak shishi be-Sivan be-chinat mitzad ha-noten. God, he wanted to give it
on the third day, on the 50th day of the עומר. But
משה Moshe said add a day. So what he actually said is
we don't call it זמן קבלת התורה, zman kabbalat ha-Torah, we call
it זמן מתן תורה. zman matan Torah. So his point is that
God, God planned, at least according to רבי יוסי, it doesn't work
according to the רבנן, but he tries to fit it in anyway.
God would have wanted to give it on the 50th, but
but משה said: No, no, no, we're not ready to receive it
on Thursday on Friday, we're going to get it on שבת. So
the מתן תורה matan Torah is the 50th, but the קבלה kabbalah
of the תורה Torah, is the day later. And you know, again
it works in very nice with the idea that משה was מוסיף
יום אחד מדעתו, mosif yom echad mi-da'ato, sort of again this human
component. To give the תורה Torah, requires a receiver, you know, the
whole idea of תורה שבכתב Torah she-bi-chtav and תורה שבעל פה Torah
she-ba'al peh and the partnership. So if the receiver wasn't ready to
get it till the day later, so we can celebrate the day
that God wanted to give the תורה, Torah but it actually does
work out nicely with two days יום טוב Yom Tov for חוץ
לארץ, chutz la-aretz, right, so we were only ready the next day
and that was actually the day that we received it. Yes.
According to סדר עולם Seder Olam the... yeah, it works out.
The
Exodus was on Friday, yes, 15 ניסן can never fall on a
Friday with the current calendar.
With the current calendar, you know, when you're doing it based on
קידוש החודש, kiddush ha-chodesh, it all is... it's all fair game. Yes,
two quick questions and we move on. Yes. Is it a problem
that the...
we say that the ברייתא of סדר עולם Seder Olam is from
the רבנן, but the earlier רבנן has a פסח on a Thursday,
right, and...
No, it's saying that there are different versions, it's not that they
themselves said it. There are different versions, one would be consistent with
the approach of, you know, five day... of a two day separation,
one of a three day separation. It's just saying that there are
different approaches in the תנאים, some take the two day approach, some
take the three day approach. It's not saying that specifically, you know,
רבנן said this or רבי יוסי said that, except, you know, Charlie's
question that the סדר עולם is supposed to be רבי יוסי. Okay,
last point. Yes.
Observation that, you know, מתן תורה matan Torah is really not a
very accurate term because that was a at least a 40 day
process. Right, it's really מעמד הר סיני Ma'amad Har Sinai which we're
talking about, the beginning of that process.
Okay, there you go. Another legitimate point.
All right, and it comes to a conclusion then. So which...
Right. All right, well, moving on. I don't know. ויתייצבו Vayityatzvu now
to two famous אגדתות Aggadtot relating to הר, Har, קבלת התורה. Kabbalat
ha-Torah. ויתייצבו בתחתית ההר, Vayityatzvu be-tachtit ha-har,
they stood at the bottom of the mountain. אמר רב אבדימי, Amar
Rav Avdimi, so
בתחתית be-tachtit doesn't mean just by the foot of, but here obviously
the דרשה drasha is going to assume it means תחת tachat underneath
the mountain. So אמר רב אבדימי בר חמא בר חסדא, Amar Rav
Avdimi bar Chama bar Chisda, מלמד, melamed, very famous גמרא Gemara of
course, שכפה הקדוש ברוך הוא עליהם את ההר כגיגית, she-kafa ha-Kadosh Baruch
Hu aleihem et ha-har ke-gigit, God lifted up the mountain over them
like a barrel. They were underneath it and like a barrel raised
over somebody ready to be thrown on top of a person. ואמר
להם, Ve-amar lahem, אם אתם מקבלים את התורה מוטב, im atem mekablim
et ha-Torah mutav, if you accept the Torah good, ואם לאו, ve-im
lav, and if not, שם תהא קבורתכם, sham tehe kevuratchem, this will
be where you will be buried. So you have no choice. You'd
better accept it. So אמר רב אחא בר יעקב... Amar Rav Acha
bar Yaakov... אמר רב אחא בר יעקב amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov
מכאן מודעא רבה לאורייתא. mikan moda'ah rabbah l'Oraita. One minute, if that's
true, we never willingly accepted the Torah, we were forced to accept
it, so therefore that is a מודעא. moda'ah. מודעא moda'ah is like,
you know, is like if you're if you're going if you're being
forced to sign a contract and what you want to do is
you want to sort of, you know, negate it, let people know,
so you take some witnesses aside in a room and you inform
them, you know, that you're being that you're being compelled to sign
this contract and they testify to the fact, so then after you
sign it, you know, you're able to take out the, you know,
the document and prove that the contract was negated, that it was
done under it was done under, you know, compulsion, coercion. So here,
this is a, you know, this is a great, you know, negation
of the Torah like it's a evidence that it should be, you
know, that we were compelled, we were coerced. So אמר רבא, amar
Rava, so said Rava, oh, well I have an answer to that.
אף על פי כן הדור קבלוה בימי אחשורוש. af al pi chen
hadar kibluha b'imei Achashverosh. They accepted it in the times of אחשורוש.
Achashverosh. דכתיב, dechtiv, right,
קיימו וקבלו היהודים, kimu v'kiblu haYehudim, they accepted they fulfilled and they
accepted. So what's the double language קיימו וקבלו? kimu v'kiblu? קיימו מה
שקיבלו כבר. kimu mah shekiblu kvar. They established on themselves what they
had prior accepted out of compulsion, here they accepted it out of
free will. Now what does all of this mean? So first of
all, תוספות points out a narrative problem which is that, you know,
before it was ותתיצבו בתחתית ההר, vatyityatzvu b'tachtit hahar, it said they
said כל אשר דבר ה' נעשה. kol asher diber Hashem na'aseh. And
according to the, you know, what I just mentioned before and we're
going to say again, they didn't only say נעשה, na'aseh, they did
the whole thing of the ספר הברית Sefer HaBrit at the end
of משפטים where they said נעשה ונשמע na'aseh v'nishmah and they entered
in a ברית. brit. So what do you mean it was compelled,
you know? They willingly accepted it prior. Okay, so that's one question
that תוספות has. The other question is, well bracket that for now,
the other question is, you know, what are חז"ל Chazal trying to
get at here by this sense of, you know, of being compelled
and so on? So, you know, I don't know who was the
first one who said this, but now it is a classic explanation
of this is that what they're trying to do is give expression,
and we'll see this a little bit later as well, you know,
give expression to the idea that what does it mean to be
standing directly in the presence of God's commanding presence? You know, if
God is you really are directly experiencing God and God is saying,
you know, you must do this, where's that sense of free choice
at that moment? How can you exert your human, you know, independence
to willingly say yes or no in the direct presence of God's
commanding voice? And so and if you want to make it a
little, you know, so that's so, you know, and especially if you
want to just add the psychological component of, you know, the mountain
and the fire and the thunder and the lightning, but even without
the whole, you know, the whole fireworks show, if they really understood
that they were experiencing God and God's commanding voice, how could they
do anything but say yes? So what the גמרא Gemara is doing
is it's sort of, you know, dealing with that problem. It's fine
they said yes beforehand, but then they didn't really know yet what
God was, you know, what the content of it was, especially now,
of course, it's solved if you have the נעשה ונשמע na'aseh v'nishmah
at the end of משפטים because then they're not directly in the
presence of God, they've heard it and then afterwards they're sort of
soberly saying yes. But if you bring the נעשה ונשמע na'aseh v'nishmah
at the end of משפטים earlier, all of their agreement was prior.
When they finally heard the actual content, you know, and are they
willingly being able to choose yes or no to accept it at
that moment, what type of choice did they have? So it was
as if it was a כפה עליהם הר כגיגית. kafah aleihem har
k'gigit. It was as if they had absolutely no choice. And therefore
פורים Purim is the response to this, because פורים Purim is the
time when it would, you know, they were in גלות, galut, it
was easy to sort of believe, you know, the way חז"ל Chazal
say many Jews may have believed, you know, God has abandoned us,
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is destroyed, you know, God's name doesn't
appear anywhere in the מגילה, Megillah, it would have been easy to
deny God's presence. So it's the exact diametric opposite, as opposed to
the full force of the divine presence, it was something that would
have been easy to have seen as complete divine absence. And the
idea to assert that they saw God's hand and to assert that
they saw this as a נס, nes, you know, that was the
exact counterpart to the מעמד הר סיני Ma'amad Har Sinai where it
was a full willingness to see God and to see the relationship
to the God and their obligation to God, even when it could
have easily been denied. And so therefore that was the sort of
full willing acceptance. So that's sort of the right now I don't
know when again when that was first put out there and who
to attribute that to, but I think that's like probably the most
classic and I think powerful explanation of what is going on here.
So the מהר"ל though again because I was checking him up last
night, so he deals with an interesting question which is, you know,
okay but like what's the idea of doing both? Like if they
were going to, you know, why if you're going to do the
כפה הר כגיגית, kafah har k'gigit, so why did you need sort
of like the נעשה na'aseh and what was sort of the point
of, you know, of the כפה עליהם הר כגיגית? kafah aleihem har
k'gigit? And what he says is that he says because look, we're
about to quote the famous מדרש Midrash which I'm sure you also
know that, you know, that like the whole מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh Bereishit
were dependent on בני ישראל Bnei Yisroel accepting the תורה Torah at
הר סיני. Har Sinai. He says look... The תורה, Torah it had
to be given. Like sort of like that was the whole plan,
the whole plan was for the תורה Torah to be given and
for בני ישראל Bnei Yisroel to accept the תורה Torah. and so
on. So you did, you had to set it up that even
if they weren't going to accept it, it wouldn't couldn't have been
something that was somehow contingent. It had to be like a necessary
part of the fabric of reality that there was a תורה Torah,
and the תורה preceded the creation of the world and בני ישראל
Bnei Yisroel, were going to accept the תורה, and that's what the
מדרש Midrash will mean when it says, you know, the entire creation
was dependent on בני ישראל Bnei Yisroel accepting it. Like, you know,
this was part of the whole divine plan. It had to happen.
So in order to sort of assert the necessity of it as
part of the, you know, the fabric of reality, there had to
be this sense of it's going to happen regardless. כפה הר כגיגית.
Kaffa har kegigit. At the same time, you want it to be
a, you know, a sense of a of a willing agreement and
commitment and therefore you also do the נעשה. Naaseh. But again and
another but however another problem he does point out and this is
very interesting, you know, because he says, you know, if it was
only that willing commitment, besides the other point about sort of emphasizing
it as a necessary part of reality, he says then you would
feel look, I entered it willingly, I can leave it willingly, you
know, it's all my own choice, which is sort of the opposite
of the מודעא רבה. Modaa Rabba. The מודעא רבה Modaa Rabba is
I was forced, I don't have to do it. Okay, but the
flip side is if I'd have been forced, but you remain forced.
God still says you got to do it. It's not your choice,
you know. So the so whereas if you read the simple narrative
in the תורה, it's all we willingly entered into the covenant, so
you could go two ways with that. We willingly entered therefore we
can't back out, we decided on our own, nobody forced us to
do it, or no, it's all my choice. I willingly said yes,
now I willingly say no. So you want to have sort of
like both of those components. On the one hand, the sense that
you are a partner and you participated and that's sort of and
some ways that actually obligates you more than if it was forced.
And on the other hand, it had to happen and also regardless
of what you say it had to happen and you have no
at some level you have no choice whether you like it or
not, God is telling you you have to do it. So again
it raises this interesting question of if you would ציווי Tzivuy and
מצוה, Mitzvah, which is all about what מעמד הר סיני Maamad Har
Sinai תורה is, right? לא יהיה לך, Lo yiheyeh lecha, אנכי ה׳
אלהיך, Anochi Hashem Elokecha, it's all about God's מצוה Mitzvah and then
the surrounding narrative in the תורה is about ברית, Bris, is about
a willing contract entered in by both sides. So it's that dialectic
of ציווי Tzivuy and ברית Bris that is sort of the גמרא
Gemara is really trying to grapple with here in terms of these
two competing narratives.
Yes, this was all part of the plan that בני ישראל, Bnei
Yisrael בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael. had to accept it and what the
whole thing would be, you know, מה... Mah...
Oh come on, I'm not, I'm not going to explain all Midrashic.
Yes, is it connected to the earlier part where משה, you know,
added a day on his own?
Well yes, I do think you mean that idea that like it's
not just all about God, it's about us as well, right. And
is that is that your point, our partnership in the in the
process?
In other words, right, is it free will as משה exercised?
And it's interesting because in the previous מדרש, Midrash, God was dictating
the whole plan and the מדרש Midrash comes or that's, you know,
the idea of משה adding a day came to to introduce our
participation. Here it's almost the reverse, the תורה emphasizes the framing of
it as נעשה Naaseh before, נעשה ונשמע Naaseh Ve-nishmah after, and they're
emphasizing the sense that it was like God demanded it must be
done. So it's this ongoing dialectic between those two, yes.
To deal with the the idea like what about in between, you
know, the however many generations. Yes,
the the אחשורוש Achashverosh more or less coincides with the end of
נבואה Nevuah and so that's the the period where God has a
more direct
presence, now it becomes about our responsibility, right, in the Rabbinic
period, right.
That's a very good point, exactly, yes, very nice, yes.
Well there is later than אחשורוש Achashverosh there was under Ezra and
Nechemia, which presumably is later, there was another acceptance.
Right. Well that's right, that he read the ספר Sefer to the
people and that they, you know, yeah. So that's a very good
point
and it does fit in with Dovel's point that this is also
the time if you will of history where God's commanding presence or
God's presence is less felt and sort of our the upholding of
the ברית Bris is much more in terms of our, you know,
insistence of seeing, you know, of seeing that and of seeing God's
presence and insisting on the, you know, of our commitment to the
ברית, Bris, right. So that's very nicely said. Okay, so now yes,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues the following. אמר חזקיה, Amar Chizkiya,
מאי דכתיב? mai dichviv? What's meant by the verse משמים השמעת דין?
Mishamayim Hishmata Din? From the from the heavens you made heard the
law, ארץ יראה ושקטה, Eretz Yara Ve-shaktah, the land saw and and
was silent. אם יראה למה שקטה ואם שקטה למה יראה? Im Yara
lama Shaktah ve-im Shaktah lama Yara?
Is it יראה Yara or is it saw or feared? What do
you have there as a translation? I didn't check I must admit.
Feared. So what is it? Not יראה, Yara, it's what is it?
יראה? Yarei?
He says יראה שמא... Yara shema...
Yeah, but is it יראה Yara or יר...
what? יראה.
יראה *yara* saw or יראה *yara* feared?
They say feared. Feared.
How would you say saw? How would you say saw? Wouldn't it
also be יראה *yara*?
But it would be יראה *yara*.
ראה *ra'ah*. ארץ ראה *eretz ra'ah*.
It depends if you have a ה *hey*, יראה *yara* or יראה
*yirah*.
Uh-huh. That's what it says, ויראו אנשים *vayeeru anashim*.
Oh, with a with a דגש *dagesh*.
Correct, person. Yeah. Very מקפיד *makpid* on that.
Okay. Let's see what they say. משמים השמעת דין ארץ יראה ושקטה
*mishamayin hishmata din eretz yara veshakata*. That is cast down judgment from
heaven and the earth feared, yeah. All right, so I don't know
the grammar. I don't know the grammar, but fine. Okay, so the
land feared and it was silent. So, אם יראה למה שקטה *im
yara lama shakta*, if it was afraid, why was it silent? You're
not you're not silent when you're afraid, you tremble. ואם שקטה *veim
shakta*, and if it was silent, למה יראה *lama yara*, why was
it afraid? Meaning how do you explain this this seeming contradiction? Okay,
so אלא בתחילה יראה ולבסוף שקטה *ela betechila yara ulevasof shakata*. First
it was afraid and then it settled down. ולמה יראה *velama yara*,
what was it afraid about? כדריש לקיש *kedresh lakish*, like Resh Lakish.
דאמר ריש לקיש *deamar resh lakish* מאי דכתיב mai dechtiv, *mai dechtiv*
ויהי ערב ויהי בוקר יום השישי *vayehi erev vayehi voker yom hashishi*,
the the sixth day. What's the ה *hey*? ה יתירה למה לי
*hey yeteira lama li*? Why the extra ה *hey*? מלמד שהתנה הקדוש
ברוך הוא עם מעשה בראשית ואמר להם *melamed shehitna hakadosh baruch hu
im ma'aseh bereshit veamar lahem*, God stipulated with the מעשה בראשית *ma'aseh
bereshit* and said to them, אם ישראל מקבלים את התורה אתם מתקיימים
*im yisrael mekabelim et hatorah atem mitkaymim*, if the Jews accept the
Torah then you will be established, ואם לאו אני מחזיר אתכם לתוהו
ובוהו *veim lav ani machzir etchem letohu vavohu*, if not I will
return you to waste and nothingness. So and the ה *hey* is
the sixth day, meaning the sixth of סיון *Sivan*, at least according
to the רבנן *rabanan*, not רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosei*. Okay, so anyway,
again this point about the necessity of the Torah, the world was
created, you know, in a way this was all part of the
divine plan for the Torah to be given. So it was all
hinging on them accepting the Torah, which as I mentioned before ties
back into the מדרש Midrash *midrash* that God had to make sure
that it would happen, the כפה עליהם הר כגיגית kafah aleihem har
ke-gigit, *kafa aleihem har kegigit*.
So that יום השישי *yom hashishi* we do at the beginning of
Friday night קידוש *kiddush* is very important. Exactly. דרש רבי סימאי *darash
rabbi simai*.
So Rabbi Simai expounded. בשעה שהקדימו ישראל besha'a shehikdimu Yisrael נעשה לנשמע
na'aseh lenishmah, *besha'a shehikdimu yisrael na'aseh lenishma*. So that was about the
הר כגיגית *har kegigit* and about them accepting the Torah, you know,
and the commanding voice of God. Now we're getting to the also
the acceptance, but not the הר כגיגית *har kegigit*, the נעשה ונשמע
Na'aseh V'Nishmah. *na'aseh venishma* where they actually did the willing acceptance. Again,
this is at the end of משפטים *mishpatim*, but it's here being
assumed to have taken place before the Torah was given. בשעה שהקדימו
ישראל נעשה na'aseh לנשמע *besha'a shehikdimu yisrael na'aseh lenishma*, when they said
נעשה na'aseh *na'aseh* before נשמע nishmah, *nishma*, they put נעשה Na'aseh *na'aseh*
first. באו ששים ריבוא מלאכי השרת Malachei HaShareit לכל אחד ואחד מישראל
*bau shishim ribo malachei hasharet lechol echad veechad miyisrael*. So sixty
myriads, six hundred thousand of heavenly angels came for each one of
the Jews, meaning of course each man who between the ages of,
you know, from 20 and up. So again, he mentioned before about
the emphasis of bringing women into the picture, but here it's going
focusing on the 600,000 which is the men. So anyway, the angels
came. וכל אחד ואחד מישראל קשרו לו שני כתרים *vechol echad veechad
miyisrael kashru lo shenei ketarim*, and each one put two crowns, אחד
כנגד נעשה Na'aseh ואחד כנגד נשמע nishmah. *echad keneged na'aseh veechad keneged
nishma*, one for נעשה Na'aseh *na'aseh* and one for נשמע Nishma *nishma*.
וכיון שחטאו ישראל *vekeivan shechatu yisrael*, then when they sinned and they
made the עגל Eigel. *egel*, ירדו מאה ועשרים ריבוא מלאכי חבלה ופרקום
*yardu me'ah ve'esrim ribo malachei chabalah uperakum*. Then then 1.2 million of
angels of destruction came and removed them. Now why more? מידה טובה
*mida tova* must be better than מידה פורענות *mida pur'anuyot*. But the
point is it is, because for the מידה טובה *mida tova*, one
angel's able to give two crowns. But for the מידה פורענות *mida
pur'anuyot*, the angels are weaker, so you need more angels because the
angels are weaker. Anyway, שנאמר Shene'emar ויתנצלו בני ישראל את עדים מהר
חורב *shenemar vayitnatzlu benei yisrael et edyam mehar chorev*. They removed their
jewelry from הר חורב *har chorev*, a very curious פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*,
hard to understand in terms of the פשט *pshat*. What does it
refer to? And here the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says it is referring
to this. אמר רבי חמא בר חנינא *amar rabbi chama bar chanina*,
בחורב טענו *bechorev ta'anu*, and and הר חורב *har chorev* they put
on these crowns. ובחורב פרקו *uvechorev parku*, and they were forced to
remove them after they sinned with the עגל *egel*. בחורב טענו כדאמרן
*bechorev ta'anu keda'amaran*, like we said, which again not alluded to in
the פסוקים *psukim*, but you know, we just said that the angels
came. ובחורב פרקו דכתיב dechtiv, ויתנצלו בני ישראל *uvechorev parku dechtiv vayitnatzlu
benei yisrael*, they removed their crowns. So maybe it could be inferred
if they removed their crowns or their jewelry they must have gotten
it. They got it when they said נעשה ונשמע Na'aseh V'Nishmah. *na'aseh
venishma*. True. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan, וכולם זכה משה ונטלן
*amar rabbi yochanan vechulam zachah moshe unetalan*. And all of them Moshe
inherited and took for himself. דסמיך ליה ומשה יקח את האוהל *desamich
leh umoshe yikach et haohel*. And Moshe took the tent and it
says, you know, and and so again it seems like what it's
really referring to is not the taking of the tent, but the
fact that his face shone. So these are like these crowns give
you a certain like aura and shining and so on. The shining
of Moshe's face came because Moshe was the only one who remained,
you know, who remained faithful and therefore they all accrued to him.
Okay. ואמר ריש לקיש עתיד הקדוש ברוך הוא להחזירן לנו *veamar resh
lakish atid hakadosh baruch hu lehachziran lanu*. In the end God will
return them to us. שנאמר Shene'emar ופדויי ה' ישובון ובאו ציון ברנה
*shenemar ufduyei adonai yeshuvun uvau tziyon berina*. Those redeemed by God will
return and they'll come to ציון *Tziyon* in rejoicing. ושמחת עולם על
ראשם al rosham, *vesimchat olam al rosham*. And the joy of the
world or whatever of eternity will be on their heads. So again
the heads and the crowns. The heads and the crowns. שמחה שמעולם,
the joy that they had from the past, you know, from ages,
from way back, על ראשם, they will now again be wearing on
their heads. Okay, so all of this about the glory of the
נעשה ונשמע. Na'aseh V'Nishmah I'll read a little bit more and then
I'll reflect on the significance of this נעשה ונשמע. Na'aseh veNishma, אמר
רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, בשעה שהקדימו ישראל נעשה Na'aseh לנשמע, when
they had נעשה Na'aseh preceded נשמע, Nishma. יצתה בת קול ואמרה להן,
Yatzta bat kol ve'amra lahen, a heavenly voice came out and said
to them, מי גילה לבני רז זה, mi gila livnai raz zeh,
who revealed to my children this secret, שמלאכי השרת משתמשים בו, shemalachei
hasharet mishtamshim bo, the heavenly angels use it? דכתיב, Dechtiv ברכו ה׳
מלאכיו גבורי כח עושי דברו לשמוע בקול דברו, Barchu Hashem malachav giborei
koach osei devaro lishmoa bekol devaro, bless God, His angels, those of
strength who do
His work, to hear the voice of His word. ברישא עושי, breisha
osei, first they do the word, והדר לשמוע, vehadar lishmoa, and then
to listen. So first comes נעשה Na'aseh and then נשמע. Nishma. אמר
רבי חמא ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chama berabbi Chanina, מאי דכתיב, Mai
d'chtiv what's meant by the verse כתפוח בעצי היער, ketapuach be'atzei haya'ar,
like an apple in the you know amongst trees of the forest,
so is my beloved? So beloved here classically God is the man
and בני ישראל is the woman in the way the metaphor of
how חזל see שיר השירים. Shir HaShirim. למה נמשלו ישראל לתפוח? Lama
nimshalu Yisrael letapuach? Why are they compared to an apple? לומר לך,
lomar lach, to tell you, מה תפוח זה פריו קודם לעליו, mah
tapuach zeh piryo kodem le'alav, the same way an apple the fruit
comes out before the
leaves, אף ישראל הקדימו נעשה לנשמע. af Yisrael hikdimu na'aseh lenishmah. Now
by the way apples the fruit does not come out before the
leaves. רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says that apple does not mean apple.
Apple actually is not a Mediterranean fruit. So it'd be pretty funny
that שיר השירים Shir HaShirim would be referring to an apple. So
he actually claims that an apple is an אתרוג etrog and that
אתרוג etrog stays for many years, so by the second year already
the fruit is still there and the leaf has not yet re-emerged
for the next year. But it's clear whatever תפוח tapuach is, it
isn't an apple because apple was not a Mediterranean fruit. Anyway, what
can I tell you? I mean apple is used commonly as a
generic for fruit, right? תפוחי אדמה, tapuchei adama, you know, and so
on, pomme de terre like in French or whatever. Anyway, okay. So
now, ההוא צדוקי, Hahu Tzeduki, one more thing about נעשה ונשמע Na'aseh
veNishma and then I'll talk about it. ההוא צדוקי, Hahu Tzeduki, a
certain Sadducee. Now it is not Sadducee, the original גרסא girsa is
מין, min, a heretic, which means
classically a Jewish Christian. So it's quite interesting actually because I wanted
to check ArtScroll sometimes is good restoring the original text. So they've
restored the text to ההוא מין, hahu min, but they translated as
a Sadducee.
I don't know.
They must have given out the assignment to different people. צדוקי. Tzeduki.
Okay. No but look in the English side, I think they've got
it right. They okay. ההוא צדוקי Hahu Tzeduki דחזייא לרבא, dachazya leRava,
a certain well anyway ההוא מין hahu min דחזייא לרבא, dachazya leRava,
so certain whatever heretic or say it's a Jewish Christian who saw
רבא Rava דקא מעיין בשמעתא, deka ma'ayan bishma'ta, he was so engrossed
in his learning, ויתבה אצבעתיה דידיה תותי כרעיה, veyatva etzba'atei didey tutei
karchai,
and his fingers of his hands were like underneath his legs, like
you know sometimes you want to concentrate or whatever I surely a
classic shteiging position in the ישיבה, yeshiva, you sit with your hands
on your you know your your arms on your hands and you're
like totally like focused. So that's what he was doing. וקא מייץ
בהו, veka mayetz behu, he was squeezing his fingers with his legs.
He wasn't aware what he was doing he was so engrossed, וקא
מבען אצבעתיה דמא, veka miv'an etzba'atei dama, and his fingers were like
you know were sprouting blood. He wasn't aware what he was doing.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said to him, עמא פזיזה, ama
peziza, a sort of a impetuous nation, דקדמיתו פומייכו לאודנייכו, dekadmitu pumaichu
le'udnaichu, you were so you know you weren't thoughtful, you put your
mouth before your ears. For first you said you'll do before you
said you'll even listen. So you're just you know you don't give
thought to things before you do them you're just too passionate too
impetuous. אכתי בפזיזותייכו קיימיתו, achti bifzizutaichu kayimitu,
you're still with that same impetuousness because here you are you're not
aware of what you're doing you just do you don't pay attention
you know and therefore look you're even hurting yourself in the
process. ברישא איבעי לכו למשמע, breisha ibei lachon lemishma, at first you
should have listened, אי מציתו קבליתו, ei matzitu kablitu, if you
were able you accept, ואי לא לא קבליתו, ve'ei lo lo kablitu,
and if not you don't accept it. So you gotta be more
rational about it, not so impetuous, I'll do it regardless. Okay, now
if by the way if this is about a Jewish Christian which
most of these מין min stories are then presumably there's a subtext
here of you know about the whole idea about the law and
you know the Christians sort of challenging the idea that the law
was given you know to the Jews because they you know they
needed the law and God has now you know rejected that and
so on and that the whole idea of so to here you
say look you know this is the problem. The problem is that
You know, you accepted this without thinking, but really the law is
not the ideal, so you should have thought it through. So אמר
ליה *amar leh* he said to him, אנן *anan* דסגינן בשלימותא *disargin
bishleimuta*, we that we have complete faith in God. We have no
questions. If God says something, we trust God that it will be
what's deserving. כתיב *ktiv* by us, תומת ישרים תנחם *tumat yesharim tanchem*,
the
innocence of the righteousness will lead them. We had complete faith in
God, we were righteous, and we believe that that'll all work out
for our best. הנך אינשי *hanach inshi*, these people, meaning you guys,
דסגינן בעלילותא *disargin bealiluta*, that you look for excuses or for complaints,
not complaints, but whatever, you know, ways to criticize. כתיב בהו *ktiv
behu*, it says to you, וסלף בוגדים ישדם *veselef bogdim yeshadem*, and
the perversiveness of those who rebel
will destroy them. So basically it's like, I don't know about you,
but we trust God. So if God said that we needed the
תורה *Torah*, we believe God that we were supposed to accept the
תורה *Torah*, we don't have to think about it. You've decided you
don't need the law, you reject it, that's not us, we accepted
the law. So what is the whole emphasis here about the נעשה
ונשמע Na'aseh veNishma, *na'aseh venishma*? Part of it, why is it made
into this huge thing? Right? I mean, it's one of the first
things they tell you in like second grade, right? The whole נעשה
ונשמע Na'aseh veNishma *na'aseh venishma* was so amazing. So what was amazing
about it? So one is, of course, this sense of like, we're
not, you know, we trust God. We're not going to wait to
decide, you know, if it makes sense, it doesn't make sense, we
accept it regardless, we totally submit ourselves to God's authority. God says
it, we'll do, right? If I say jump, you don't say why,
you say how high. So that's like the נעשה Naaseh, *na'aseh* before
the נשמע Nishma. *nishma*. And that certainly seems to be the emphasis
of the angels, right? The angels don't have their own free will.
So they do, עושי דברו *osei devaro*, they first do the עשייה
*asiyah*, right? It's not about them sort of deciding should they or
shouldn't they or so on. Now, read that way, it makes the
נשמע Nishma. *nishma* very sort of trivial. Again, by the way, it's
continuing to play out the whole discussion earlier about the divine command
versus our free will. So here, too, within the נעשה ונשמע Na'aseh
veNishma *na'aseh venishma* as well, it sort of says, yes, we chose
to be part of the ברית *brit*, we used our free will,
but part of our using of our free will was to say
we're going to sort of
bracket our decision process or we'll just decide based on trust in
You, not based on our own sort of on You, on our
own criteria. So it's very interesting, introducing even within the willing acceptance,
the idea of, right, we accept it because we trust You. We
don't even have to sort of think about it. So anyway, that
goes to that element of you do, you don't ask, you accept,
you have trust in God. Read that way, of course, it downplays
the significance of the נשמע Nishma *nishma*. The נשמע Nishma *nishma* here
is like the leaf of the apple, you know, it's very insignificant.
So I just wanted to mention, and I'm just slightly sensitive about
time, a very nice thing that the שפת אמת *Sfas Emes* has
about this. He has sort of two things about the נעשה ונשמע
naaseh v'nishma, *na'aseh venishma*. So in משפטים *Mishpatin*, he twice sort of
emphasizes this idea
about the emphasis about our primary purpose is to do what God
says. This is the נעשה Naaseh *na'aseh*.
So he says like this: כשהקדימו נעשה לנשמע *kshehikdimu na'aseh lenishma*, שהיה
חביב ביניהם יותר לעשות רצונו יתברך מנשמע שהוא השגת הטעמים *shehaya chaviv
beneihem yoter la'asos retzono yisbarech minishma shehu hasagas hata'amim*. So he says
the נשמע *nishma* is not just the נשמע *nishma* of let's decide
if we want to do it, but what's this all about? Why
are we doing it? Not why should we do it, but why
are we doing it? Like טעמי המצוות *ta'amei hamitzvos*.
What's the purpose of שבת *Shabbat*? What's the purpose of, you know,
of all of these things? But before you worry about the purpose
of it, the first position should be, and this is always the
challenge of טעמי המצוות *ta'amei hamitzvos*. The challenge of טעמי המצוות *ta'amei
hamitzvos* is you want to give greater depth to your observance, it
shouldn't be rote observance, it shouldn't be blind obedience, but on the
other hand, as soon as you start giving reasons, then maybe you
might not do it, you don't like the reasons, there's other ways
of satisfying the reasons. So it's balancing the sense of we do
it regardless, but we're also supposed to understand the purpose and what
it's supposed to achieve because that adds greater depth and translates in
other ways. So your first position has to be, you do it,
before you understand the reasons, regardless of whether you like the reasons
or don't, or do you know the reasons, you do it. That's
the נעשה *na'aseh*. Okay, but before you understand the reasons, וכן זכו
*vechein zachu*, once that was your position, זכו להשיג הטעמים *zachu lehasig
hata'amim*, then you'd be able to understand the reasons. Okay? If that's
your basic way, if that's your basic orientation. And then he goes
on to say: כי הטעמים יותר פנימיים מגוף המצוות *ki hata'amim yoter
pnimiyim miguf hamitzvos*. The reasons are even more the essence than the
actual doing of the מצוות mitzvot *mitzvot*. They're ultimately what they're based
on. And that if you understand the reasons, he ties it into
אלה המשפטים *Eileh Hamishpatim*, which is again the human component, then you're
able to then have
participate in how to apply the מצוה *mitzvah*, understand their scope, you
become part of the participant. participant in the מצוות once you understand
the reasons, and that's ultimately their essence, but you can't get to
that level unless it starts with a prior a priori commitment of
obedience and to doing. So it's very beautiful in the sense that
look, you know, that has to be the foundation, but it's not
that that's what it's all about. Once that's your foundation, the commitment,
then you get to understanding the reasons which in a way is
even more essential and that allows you to be a participant in
the whole process. So that's one passage he has. The other one
which he has back in יתרו is he quotes a beautiful מדרש
Midrash which is very obscure I think obscure I have I mean
it's there it's in the מדרש רבה Midrash Rabbah but it's it's
rarely quoted. And here's what the מדרש Midrash says about after the
חטא העגל. Chet HaEigel. It says after the חטא העגל Chet HaEigel
it says עברתם נעשה, Avartem Na'aseh, okay, you guys you blew נעשה
with the חטא העגל, Chet HaEigel, you said you were going to
do and look what you did. Anyway, הזהרו בנשמע, hizaru biNishma, at
least try to keep the נשמע going. Okay. And what he says
that means is he says not everybody is זוכה zocheh to first
accept a life of commitment, you know, you know, also like if
people are deciding about, you know, becoming פרום frum or whatever, sometimes
you say look, just, you know, just start doing it and then
you'll see and you'll be able to find meaning in it and
so on. But you know what? Not everybody is in that position
to first do the נעשה and then the נשמע. So he says
it's some people they need to get to the נעשה through the
נשמע. They need to first grapple with the reason and understand the
reason so you know maybe there was a problem it talks about
it being a little overhasty. We just committed to do without even
thinking about it well maybe it made it very easy for us
then to stop doing it when it came to the חטא העגל.
Chet HaEigel. So for sometimes actually you know just focusing on the
נעשה we could wind up blowing the נעשה but at least we
have a way back in through the נשמע. If it's not through
that a priori commitment then it can come back through the נשמע.
So he says like this he says
שיוכלו עוד להשיג השמיעה משל מה אל בני
בוזרו שאחר שחטאו וקלקלו נעשה נשאר להם להתדבק על ידי השמיעה. sheyuchlu
od lehasig hashmiyah mashal milma et bnei bizru she'achar shechatu vekilkelu Na'aseh
nishar lahem lehitdabek al yedei hashmiyah. Okay. So he says you know
so even though ideally we should just be doing it because we
accept God's command but sometimes when we you know sometimes we have
to when we've abandoned that we have to find the way back
in through the through the נשמע it's sort of like the famous
מדרש Midrash which is actually forget that. Okay. So anyway so anyway
that's I thought that those were some beautiful issues around the dialectic
of the נעשה ונשמע, you know talking about how both of them
serve as ways in and about how both of them are critical.
Okay. So now the גמרא continues.
Where are we? Okay. פ"ח עמוד ב'. Peh chet amud bet.
So אמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן. amar Rav Shmuel
bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan. מאי דכתיב mai d'chtiv, what's meant by
the פסוק. pasuk Now we had quoted שיר השירים Shir HaShirim before
so now we're going to continue that. לבבתני אחתי כלה לבבתני באחת
מעיניך. Libavtini achoti kallah libavtini beachat me'einayich.
You have you have like drawn my heart with your my you
know my sister the bride with one of your eyes. בתחילה באחת
מעיניך, Batchila beachat me'einayich,
first just one of your eyes when you accepted, לכשתעשה l'chashe'tasah
once you start performing the מצוות then בשתי עיניך bishtei einayich with
both of your eyes. So here it's a different form of the
נעשה ונשמע not just your commitment of the נעשה ונשמע, but the
fact is yeah you might have put נעשה first in your words
but still the commitment came before the doing. So okay step one
was good you committed. Once you actually begin to do then that
will solidify really the relationship. אמר עולא Amar Ulla said עולא Ulla
עלובה כלה מזנה בתוך חופתה. Aluvah kallah mezaneh betoch chuppatah.
Now we're pointing out again sort of relevant to that מדרש Midrash
I just read to you the irony right oh so amazing נעשה
ונשמע and now saying yeah but it didn't exactly work out that
way did it like it'll be great once you start actually acting
on it and what happened? First chance they got they made the
עגל. So you know how you know how impetuous is it how
disgraceful is it a bridegroom a bride who commits adultery right under
her חופה chuppah right there at the foot of הר סיני we
went and we worshipped you know the the golden calf which is
often compared to זנות zenut right ויזנו אחרי אלהי נכר. viznu acharei
elohei nechar. We gave our fidelity to another god. So אמר רב
מרי ברה דבת שמואל amar Rav Mari bra deBat Shmuel מאי קרא
mai kra where's the פסוק Pasuk you see this an allusion to
this? עד שהמלך במסבו Ad shehamelech bimesibo while the king is at
in his you know in his party in his feast which is
the wedding feast נרדי נתן ריחו nirdi natan reicho my you know
my fragrance has you know has you know sort of dissipated. נתן
ריחו natan reicho the the smell went away. So the whole you
know the whole beautiful relationship it all turned sour while we were
still at the wedding feast. So אמר רב amar Rav so says
רב Rav עדיין חביבותא היא גבן adayin chavivuta hi gaban even after
that event God still has his love for us. דכתיב נתן natan
that that the fragrance went away sort of it left ולא כתיב
הסריח velo chtiv hisriach that the it stenched it spoiled. So even
after the חטא העגל Chet HaEigel it didn't totally ruin everything. But
again this גמרא the juxtaposition of oh my god נעשה ונשמע מלאכי
השרת and the whole thing I mean in a way you had
it before then they had the חטא העגל Chet HaEigel the crowns
were taken off you know so after that amazing thing fine that
was great that you had that commitment now let's carry through. let's
see that it leads through into the and again, that מדרש Midrash,
that I quoted to you about the okay, you blew the נעשה,
maybe you get the נשמע right and that would be a way
back to the נעשה as well. Okay, תנו רבנן: Tano Rabbanan: because
we mentioned the phrase עלובה, Aluva, now we're going to take an
unrelated ברייתא connecting to this word of עלובה. Aluva. עלובים ואינם עולבים,
Aluvim ve'einam olvim, those that are sort of, you know, disgraced and
they don't return
the disgrace. שומעים חרפתם ואינם משיבים, Shomim cherpatam ve'einam meshivim, hear them,
hear their theirselves being sort of embarrassed, cursed out, and they don't
denigrate and they don't respond. עושים מאהבה ושמחים בייסורים, Osim me'ahava u'smeichim
b'yisurim, serve God out of love and rejoice in affliction. Pretty hard
to reach this מדרגה, madrega, I'll tell you. עליהם הכתוב אומר, Aleihem
hakatuv omer, regarding them the פסוק Pasuk? says, ואוהביו כצאת השמש בגבורתו.
v'ohavav k'tzet hashemesh b'gevurato. Those that love God, there will be like
when the sun comes out in its strength, you know, theirs will
be the greatest reward. Okay, back to our discussion about הר סיני.
אמר רבי יוחנן, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the פסוק?
Pasuk? ה' יתן אומר המבשרות צבא רב. Hashem yiten omer hamevaserot tzava
rav. God will give speech that tells of great צבא, tzava, great
hosts. So כל דיבור ודיבור שיצא מפי הגבורה, kol dibur v'dibur sheyatza
mipi hagevura, every word that came out of God's mouth, נחלק לשבעים
לשונות, nechlak l'shivim leshonot,
is divided into 70, you know, 70 languages. So God's one word
is צבא רב tzava ra is many hosts because, you know, because
they are שבעים לשונות. shivim leshonot. Now שבעים לשונות shivim leshonot is
different than what we're about to say in a minute. That might
just be the point about, you know, this sense that the divine
word is above human speech, and when it comes into, you know,
and is expressed in human speech, in some way it's an part
of an interpretation of the of the inability to fully, you know,
you know, it's a limiting of the of the essence of the
word. So therefore, you know, there's 70 different different translations of it,
and each one gives a different nuance to exactly that ultimate speech
of God's words. So that's the idea of שבעים לשונות, shivim leshonot,
and it based also the sense that a lot of what it
means depends on who's listening, you know, and the idea of translation
and for different people it's translated differently. Now the גמרא says, תנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, another famous מדרש, Midrash וכפטיש
יפוצץ סלע, u'chfatish yefotzetz sela, like a hammer that shatters a rock.
מה פטיש זה נחלק לכמה ניצוצות, mah patish zeh nechlak l'kama nitzotzot,
the same way when a hammer bangs on a rock and many
sparks fly out, אף כל דיבור ודיבור שיצא מפי הקדוש ברוך הוא,
af kol dibur v'dibur sheyatza mipi hakadosh baruch hu, every word that
came out of God's mouth נחלק לשבעים לשונות, nechlak l'shivim leshonot, again
separated into 70 languages. One word of God, but from that one
word come many different possible understandings and interpretations.
Same as we just said before?
Sounds to be the same. Okay, אמר רב חננא בר פפא, Amar
Rav Chanana bar Pappa, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the
verse שמעו כי נגידים אדבר, shim'u ki negidim adaber, listen that I
will speak נגידים? negidim? So here נגידים, negidim, נגיד nagid can often
mean like a ruler. So למה נמשלו דברי תורה כנגיד, lama nimshalu
divrei Torah k'nagid, why are the words of תורה compared to a
ruler? לומר לך, lomar lach, מה נגיד זה יש بو להמית ולהחיות,
the same way a ruler has the power to to kill and
to give life, אף דברי תורה יש בהם להמית ולהחיות, af divrei
Torah yesh bahem l'hamit u'l'hachayot, same with the words of תורה. היינו
דאמר רבא, Hainu d'amar Rava, and now what does that mean? Like
רבא Rava says, למיימינים בה, l'mayminim bah, you know,
you know, what is it? בימינה אורך ימים בשמאלה עושר וכבוד. b'yimina
orech yamim b'smola osher v'chavod. So למיימינים בה, l'mayminim bah, those that
take the right hand approach to תורה, do it לשם שמים, l'shem
shamayim, do it with self sacrifice, סמא דחיי, sama d'chayei, that'll be
a potion of life, it'll be a, you know, a medicine of
life, it'll give you
life. למשמאילים בה, l'masmilim bah, those that take the left hand approach,
so סמא דמותא, sama d'mota, which is which is worse than the
ובשמאלה עושר וכבוד. u'v'smola osher v'chavod. So there's two always versions of
the שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. There's שלא לשמה shelo lishma which you're
not doing it for the ideal reason or with sufficient self sacrifice
but still not with like a negative intent. Then there's the שלא
לשמה shelo lishma which seems to be referred to here, the left
hand approach, which is you're doing it actually as a way to
destroy, to challenge, to attack, and then it can be a a
could be a way of death. דבר אחר, davar acher, another read
of this, נגידים, negidim, כל דיבור ודיבור kol dibur v'dibur and this
is tying into what we said before, every word שיצא מפי הקדוש
ברוך הוא, sheyatza mipi hakadosh baruch hu, קושרים לו שני כתרים. koshirim
lo sheni ketarim. So נגידים negidim is an officer, a king, a
ruler who has crowns. So again, every word has these two crowns,
presumably again tied into the נעשה ונשמע,
and you know there's the נגידים negidim is in the plural. So
again, the understanding of them and then the doing of them. אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, מאי דכתיב, mai
dichtiv? what's meant back to שיר השירים, Shir HaShirim, what's meant by
the פסוק? צרור המור דודי לי בין שדי ילין, tzeror hamor dodi
li bein shadai yalin, a bundle of myrrh is my beloved to
me, he will rest between my breasts. So אמרה כנסת ישראל לפני
הקדוש ברוך הוא, amra knesset Yisrael lifnei hakadosh baruch hu, רבונו של
עולם, ribbono shel olam, master of the universe, אף על פי שמיצר
ומימר לי, af al pi she'meitzar u'meimar li, even though you have
afflicted me what did God afflict them? So רש"י Rashi says basically,
well you punished us after the חטא העגל, chet ha'egel, so now
they're a little bit now we're getting our say, okay okay we
sinned but but We feel a little bit rejected by You. So
nevertheless, דודי בין שדי ילין, Dodi bein shadai yalin, You still stay
with me. And Rashi says this refers to the fact that even
after the חטא העגל, Cheit HaEigel, there was the ציווי tzivui of
the משכן. Mishkan. And very often in חז״ל, Chazal, the משכן Mishkan
and the poles of the ארון Aron are compared to the breasts
of a woman and they protrude out from the
פרוכת, parochet, as bumps from the פרוכת, parochet, and that's this very
intimate
husband-wife man-woman sense of intimacy of God and בני ישראל. So You
still have chosen to be present between the poles of the ארון
Aron and to be present in our midst even after the חטא
העגל. Cheit HaEigel. אשכול הכפר דודי לי בכרמי עין גדי, Eshkol hakofer
dodi li b'karmei Ein Gedi, a cluster of henna, my beloved is
to me in the vineyards of Ein Gedi. So
מי שהכל שלו, Mi shehakol shelo, God who is master of
all, יכפר, yechaper, כופר, kofer, will atone, will be able to give
atonement for me עון גדי avon gedi for the gedi, for the
goat. Now it was a calf, not a goat, but it was
an animal, close enough. So again, we're recognizing yes, we sinned, but
in the end God will atone for us, God dwelled among us,
it didn't end with חטא העגל. Cheit HaEigel. Now what's בכרמי עין
גדי? b'karmei Ein Gedi? שכרמתי לי, shekaramti li, that I gathered to
me, somehow כרם kerem means to gather. מה עין? mah ein? עין
ein is עון, avon, so בכרמי עין גדי b'karmei Ein Gedi that
I gathered for me the sin of the גדי. gedi. So מאי
משמע דהאי כרמי לישנא דמכנש הוא? Mai mashma dehai karmei lishna demichnash
hu? Where do you say the language of כרמי karmei means to
gather? So אמר מר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן Amar Mar Zutra breih
deRav Nachman כדתנן kidtnan like we taught, כסא של כובס שכרמין עליו
את הכלים, kisei shel koves shekarmin alav et hakailim, talking about different
types of vessels, טומאה וטהרה, Tumah v'Taharah, can't get out of that,
that the chair of the launderer that you gather upon it and
place upon it all the different types of
clothes. That's again the שיר השירים Shir HaShirim going from the קבלת
התורה Kabbalat HaTorah to the sin מלכי במסבו נרדי נתן ריחו malki
bimisibo nerdi natan reicho and in the end God still is with
us. So we're reading all of this into שיר השירים. Shir HaShirim.
ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי V'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi מאי דכתיב?
Back to שיר השירים. Shir HaShirim. לחייו כערוגת הבושם, Lechayav k'arugat habosem,
His cheeks are like
a field or whatever
of aromatic spices. כל דיבור ודיבור שיצא מפי הקדוש ברוך הוא, Kol
dibbur v'dibbur sheyatza mipi HaKadosh Baruch Hu, every word that came from
God's mouth, נתמלא כל העולם כולו בשמים, nitmalei kol ha'olam kulo besamim,
was so beautiful like every word the whole world was filled with
fragrance, which is interesting in contrast to the awe and the terror
that we normally are associating, and the פטיש יפוצץ סלע, patish yefotzetz
sela, the words that are breaking rocks, and שבעים לשונות, shiv'im leshonot,
here it's this very beauty and it's something that sort of draws
your heart, it fills the world
with fragrance. וכיון שמדיבור ראשון נתמלא, V'keivan shemidibbur rishon nitmalei, if after
the first word the world was filled with fragrance, דיבור שני להיכן
הלך? dibbur sheini l'heichan halach? How did the second word do anything
in terms of the fragrance? So it says, הוציא הקדוש ברוך הוא
הרוח מאוצרותיו, hotzi HaKadosh Baruch Hu haruach me'otzrotav, so what God did
was He took the wind out of His storehouse, והיה מעביר ראשון
ראשון, v'hayah ma'avir rishon rishon, and He made the first fragrance go
away so the second word you could smell the unique fragrance of
presumably each word also had a unique fragrance and you could smell
that. It's like what you have to cleanse your palate between the
courses. שנאמר Shene'emar שפתותיו שושנים, shiftotav shoshanim, His lips are like roses,
נוטפות מור עובר, notfot mor over, drip myrrh. אל תקרי שושנים
אלא ששונים, Al tikrei shoshanim ela sheshonim, don't read roses but that
learnt. So normally we'd refer that to people that learn
and an attitude towards learning. But here it says God from whose
lips came, that taught us, so the fragrance passed after each word
the fragrance passed and we received another word with more fragrance. It's
the same phrase as in
the סליחות. selichot. It's the same thing we use in the סליחות
selichot about God passing away the sins. Here it's used in a
very different context. I was wondering about that, whether it was an
allusion to it or whether it was a common phrase. I didn't
check on it. ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי V'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi כל דיבור ודיבור שיצא מפי הקדוש ברוך הוא, kol dibbur v'dibbur
sheyatza mipi HaKadosh Baruch Hu, every word that came out of God's
mouth, יצאה נשמתן של ישראל. yatz'ah nishmatan shel Yisrael. When the word
came out, their souls departed. It was so powerful that their souls
flew away. שנאמר she-ne'emar נפשי יצאה בדברו, nafshi yatz'ah bedabro, my soul
left in His
speech. ומאחר שמדיבור ראשון יצאה נשמתן, Umi'achar shemidibbur rishon yatz'ah nishmatan, if
their souls had already departed from their first speech, דיבור שני איך
קיבלו? dibbur sheini eich kibblu? How did they get to the second
דיבור? dibbur? So הוריד טל שעתיד להחיות בו מתים, horid tal she'atid
l'hachayot bo meitim, this ties into also the fragrance
idea. God took the rain that He would eventually use to resuscitate
the dead, והחיה אותם, v'hechaya otam, and He gave them
life. שנאמר גשם נדבות תניף אלהים נחלתך ונלאה אתה כוננתה. Geshem nedavot
tanif Elohim nachalat-cha v'nil'ah atah konantah. A gracious rain You have bestowed
upon them, God, to Your inheritance, they have wearied and You have
established. So this rain that gave them back
life. חזרו ישראל לאחוריהם י"ב מיל chazru Yisrael l'achoreihem yod-bet mil when
again the sense of the awe and the tremor, you know, so
we talked about their soul departing, we talked about the mountain over
them like a barrel, the awe and tremor, here we're saying they
they sort of, you know, retreated twelve mil, the entire length width
of the camp, you know, they all, you know, they all moved
back. והיו מלאכי השרת מדדין אותן Ve-hayu mal’achei ha-shareit medadin otan and
God had to send the angels to like push them, like you
know, forward, to you know, to get them to to get them
to like,
what do you call that, like when you walk an infant? מדדה,
medadeh, like I don't know, anyway, that's the word מדדה. medadeh. What
is that? Toddle?
Anyway, I don't know, anyway, to somehow to somehow get them to
to you know, to push them, they made little baby steps back.
שנאמר as the verse says, מלכי צבאות ידודון ידודון, Malchei tzeva'ot yedodun
yedodun, angels of the host will, so one way it means that
they themselves will like sort of gather around and will like walk.
אל תקרי ידודון אלא ידדון, Al tikrei yedodun ela yedaddun, they will
make others walk, they pushed us back into the place. So I'll
end since I've been bringing a lot of extra sources, I mean
there's such a rich גמרא with something from Emil Fackenheim's book, God's
Presence in History, it's a great book. Anyway, he says here similar
to the point I said before about the כפה עליהם הר כגיגית,
kafah aleihem har ke-gigit. he quotes a מדרש Midrash though that's very
similar to the מדרש Midrash we just read and here's the מדרש
he quotes. רבי עזריה ורבי אחא בשם רבי יוחנן Rabbi Azaryah ve-Rabbi
Acha be-shem Rabbi Yochanan said, when the Israelites heard at Sinai the
word I, אנכי, Anochi, their souls left them, as it says, if
we hear the voice anymore we will die. The word then returned
to the Holy One blessed be He and said, Sovereign of the
universe, Thou art full of life and Thy law is full of
life and Thou hast sent me to the dead, they're all dead.
Thereupon the Holy One blessed be He sweetened the word for them.
So same idea, so what does he say this means, he says
like this, he says that the divine presence here is a commanding
presence,
okay,
because it is a commanding rather than saving presence, the abiding astonishment
turns into deadly terror. Indeed, such a presence is in its first
instant nothing short of paradoxical, for being commanding it addresses human freedom
and being the sole power it destroys the freedom because it's only
human, sort of like the כפה עליהם הר כגיגית. Hence, the divine
commanding presence can be divine commanding and present only if it is
doubly present. As sole power it destroys human freedom and as a
gracious power it restores the freedom and indeed exalts it, for human
freedom is part of the covenant of the divinity itself. So gives
a very beautiful expression to these מדרשים midrashim of the words both
sort of causing their soul to depart but also resuscitating them, that
encountering God's word in one way destroys our freedom, but the whole
point is to make us free agents to willingly choose and to
be able to hear and to do.